Is this... the island where the people outside living?
これが… 外の人間が住んでいた島…？
Isn't it abandoned?
廃虚じゃないか
Tell me the truth.
…どういうことだ
You don't mean this is your world right?
これがお前らの世界だっていうのかよ
Oni, stop it!
オウニ やめろ！
Oni!
オウニ！
Seems you guys actually don't know anything.
あなたたちは　本当に何も知らないのね
We did not know anything.
私たちは何も知らなかった
Nothing other than the mud whale... Nothing.
泥クジラ以外の世界を　何も…
Translator
字 幕 入 力
ssnake
ssnake
静寂よ　旋律よ　儚き印よ
静寂よ　旋律よ　儚き印よ
Timing
字 幕 編 集
zwc1991
zwc1991
砂上にこの地に　生き続けたのなら
砂上にこの地に　生き続けたのなら
罪を纏う世界から　鯨の歌を聴いた…
罪を纏う世界から　鯨の歌を聴いた…
運命を　感情を　抱くべき子たちよ
運命を　感情を　抱くべき子たちよ
さ き
さ  き
その先へ　その未来へ
その先へ　その未来へ
導かれたのなら
導かれたのなら
幾千の声　空想の地へ
幾千の声　空想の地へ
舵を切って行こうとした
舵を切って行こうとした
バラード
バラード
幾千の声　砂の海の譚歌
幾千の声　砂の海の譚歌
What's this?
何だ？　これは
Graves.
お墓よ
So many friends and fellows died...
友達や仲間をこんなに…？
They are all buried by yourself?
これを…君が一人で送ったの…？
How can you be this calm,
これを淡々と一人でやったってのかよ
you witch.
…魔女だな
Why... Why did so many people have to die?
なぜ…こんなたくさんの人が死ななきゃならなかったの…？
I pray, for the people who I don't know.
お祈りするね　誰か知らない人たち
Hey, where are you heading?
おい　どこに向かってるんだ？
Here.
ここよ
Waa!
うわああ！
Hey, what's this?
おい　これは何だ？
Answer me.
答えろ
Lykos?
リコス？
λύκος
λύκος
Lykos is not my name.
「リコス」は私の名前じゃない
νοῦς
ヌース
It's the name of this creature called nous.
この魂形と呼ばれる生き物の名前よ
Creature?
生き物？
Νοῦς
ヌース
Nous, means the shape of soul,
魂形…　魂の形
is a creature that absorbs emotions from human beings.
人の「感情」を吸収して喰べる生き物
We have been...
私たちは…
λύκος
λύκος
feeding Lykos with our feelings as its nutrition.
自分の感情をこの「リコス」に栄養分として与えてきた
That's why we have flat minds.
だから私たちの心はのっぺらぼう
νοῦς
ヌース
People who discovered the nous decided to deposit their emotions with them.
魂形を発見した人々は感情を預けることにした
Cuz emotions will destroy the world.
感情は世界を滅ぼすから
It's not what we need.
必要のないものだから
In the world outside, where you want to know,
あなたが知りたがっている外の世界は
απάθεια
アパトイア
people without emotions command the apatheia with no heart
感情のない人たちが心のない人形兵士を使って
to fight in an endless war.
いつ終わるとも知れない戦いを続けている…
It's such a world.
そんな世界
Is there particularly anything you want from our world?
あなたたちの求めるものは　私たちの世界にある？
Go back, and leave me here.
私を置いて帰って
I will die on this ship by myself.
私は一人で　この船で死ぬから
Lykos...
リコス…
I don't even mind.
俺は別にかまわない
I don't care if there's a war or not.
戦争だろうが何だろうが…
I just want to escape from the mud whale.
泥クジラにこのまま閉じ込められるのはごめんだ
If I can get out there,
あそこから出られるなら…
I'm willing to give all my feelings to you!
俺の感情なんていくらでもくれてやる
Stop, Oni! It's dangerous!
オウニ！　だめ　危ない…
Ah!
あっ！
What...
なに…
There are hundreds, thousands...
頭の中を何百…　何千…？
no, numbers of minds passing by and disappearing.
見たことのない数の人間の「心」がよぎっては　消えていく
Oh my, I know this chaos...
ああ　これは…　この混沌は
hypergraphia
ハイパーグラフィア
When I can't stop writing,
書くことを抑えられなくなったときに
I see this picture.
浮かぶ情景だ
Benihi?
ベニヒ…？
No, this is my memory.
だめ　これは俺の記憶
No way!
ダメだ
I'm sad for it, but I don't want to get rid of it!
悲しくたって　消したくない！
Lykos.
リコス
Hey guys!
おい！
You certainly know what you did right?
お前ら何をしたか分かってるのか？
Chakuro!
チャクロ！
Are you OK?
大丈夫？
Chakuro? Hey Chakuro!
チャクロ？　チャクロってば！
Ah... Sami?
あ…　サミ？
You saw a lot of gravestones.
数多くの墓標を見た…
Are they really the only things you have seen?
本当にそれだけかね？
Yep.
ああ
Chakuro, what about you?
チャクロは？
Yes, nothing else.
はい　ほかには何も…
Let's believe what you two said.
分かった　二人の言うことを信じよう
Taisha, tell everyone,
タイシャ　皆に伝えなさい
traveling to that island is strictly prohibited.
あの島への渡航は　一切禁止にすると
So the procurement of goods is...
では　物資の調達は…
Canceled, you can't even take a needle.
草木一本持ち込んではならん
Cool your head a bit here.
そこで頭を冷やせ
So Oni, you were OK?
オウニは大丈夫だった？
Your heart wasn't taken by that right?
心　取られてないよね？
I saw strange stuffs at that time.
俺　あのときおかしなもの見たんだ
I believe, it's an creature that can truly absorb your heart.
あれ…ほんとに心を取っちゃう生き物なのかな
For just a moment...
一瞬だけ
I saw it for a split second.
…一瞬だけ見えた
The war of the outside world
外の世界の戦争って
sentikinesis
サイミア
is a war using thymia, I think.
情念動を使った戦争なのか
That girl must be able of it, right?
…あの女も使えたんだろ？
Oni, I'd leave it far away.
オウニ　だめだよ…
Haven't you thing the graves?
あのお墓見ただろ？
I start to be scared about the world outside.
俺　外の世界が少し怖くなっちゃった
Wait, why didn't you help me at that time!
ていうか　なんで助けてくれなかったの！？
If Lycos didn't give me a...
リコスが助けてくれなかったら…
Strange.
あれ？
That's why we have flat minds.
だから私たちの心はのっぺらぼう
Then why did she help me?
だったら　なんで俺を助けようとしたんだろう…
Chakuro.
チャクロ
Masoo.
マソオさん
I'm finishing my meal...
ご飯なら　今…
Nope, you're released.
いんや　釈放
Huh?
え？
Only you.
お前だけな
There's a guy who saw you were forced to go with Oni.
お前がオウニに無理やり連れていかれたのを見た奴がいてさ
I wasn't really forced to go, though...
完全に無理やりてわけじゃなかったんだけど…
You are lucky, you get released at a good timing.
よかったなお前　いいタイミングで出られたぞ
What?
え？
Chakuro!
チャクロ〜！
Around the mud whale,
泥クジラの周囲には
there are large grasshoppers called star locust living.
「ホシボシバッタ」と呼ばれる　大柄なバッタが生息している
They live on eating wastes from the mud whale.
彼らは泥クジラから出る廃棄物などを食べ　暮らしている
They metamorphose into a structure suitable for long range movement
群れの数が増えると長期移動に適した姿へと変化し
They start emitting lights and moving far away at midnight.
深夜に光を発しながら大移動を始めるのだ
We call it a locust phenomenon.
私たちはそれを「飛蝗現象」と呼んでいた
Hurry up!
急ごう
We need to take a good place before it gets dark!
暗くなる前にいい場所取らないと
Yep yep.
へいへ〜い
Sami, Nezu, Lo,
サミ　ネズ　ロウ！
wait a moment please!
お願い　ちょっと待ってて
Hey, Chakuro!
おい　チャクロ？
Where are you going?
どこ行くのよ？
May I help you?
どうなさいました？
Are you still suffering from the injury?
怪我がまだ痛みますか？
My name is Neli, I am taking care of the presbyters at this tower.
私はこの塔で長老様たちのお世話をさせていただいている
I am just a Muin, but please don't hesitate to ask me if you need any assistance.
「無印」の身ではありますが　何なりとお申しつけください
Tell the presbyters!
長老たちへ伝えて
I need that ship!
私はあの船が必要なの
λύκος
λύκος
Get me back to Lykos!
私を「リコス」の所へ戻して…
I can't leave it.
あれが離れてしまうといけない
If I have feelings...
感情があるなんて…
I'll be mad.
私には耐えられない…
I have to take my minds away.
心を消してもらわないと…
It is normal to have minds.
心があるのは普通です
You will soon get used to it.
すぐ慣れますよ
Here you are!
いた！
Chakuro!
チャクロさん！？
Neli, please!
ネリ…お願い！
Let me take Lykos out!
リコスを連れ出してもいい？
Take her out...
連れ出すって…
You want to get sent to the internal again?
また体内送りになりますよ？
I want to see the locust with her
一緒に飛蝗を見たいんだ
as well as my friends.
リコスも…俺の仲間と一緒に
That's a deal, thank you.
じゃあ　お願いね
Neli you should take a good place as soon as possible, too.
ネリも早くいい場所に登りなよ
Leave me.
はなして
No,
ダメ
I can't leave you alone even if you don't have minds.
たとえ君に心がなくったって　ほっとけない
You made so many graves for your fellows, all by yourself.
君は一人で　あんなにたくさんの仲間のお墓を作ってあげた
I can never leave such a good girl alone.
そんな子を　このままほっとけやしないよ！
What? With Lykos?
えっ　リコスも？
The girl from that island? Great!
あの島の子？　マジかよ！
Eh... Hi, call me Nezu.
どっ…どうも　俺　ネズっていうんだ
So, what should we do?
で　どうすんだ？
If she is found, then it's much more than not being able to see the locust.
誰かに見つかったら　飛蝗見物どころじゃないぞ
No problem!
大丈夫！
By taking my anti sand cloak this way,
こうやって俺の砂よけマントをかぶせれば
she will never be recognized.
誰だか分かんないし
How you dare renting your dirty cloak to a girl
…お前　洗濯してない砂だらけの自分のマントを
without even have it washed.
よく女の子に貸せるなあ
No, give it back to me!
あっ　やっぱ返して…
But then how can I hide you!
あっ　でもそうするとバレちゃう！
There are spaces on the top of the 4th tower.
第4塔のてっぺんが空いてるね
Let's go there.
あそこにしよう
Ahh, I can't move anymore.
あ〜ん　もう無理！
I'm tired!
疲れた！
Only a few more steps to go.
もうすぐてっぺんだよ
But...
だって…
You can do it.
頑張って
Chakuro,
チャクロ…
lift me up.
だっこして
Wh... What?
は…はあ？
What are you talking about?
な…なに言ってんのさ
You lifted my up last time!
前のときはだっこしてくれた
Last time...
前の…って
The previous locust phenomenon is three years ago, right?
前の飛蝗のときって3年前だよな？
Lift me up! I can't walk anymore!
だっこ！　もう歩けない！
Yeah.
ああ
It's impossible now!
無理だよ！
You are getting heavy!
だってもうサミ重いもん！
Sami is not heavy at all!
サミ　重くないもん！
Chakuro's spiteful!
チャクロのいじわるっ！
Idiot! Stingy!
バカ！　ドケチ！
See, you can walk yourself
ほ〜ら　歩けるじゃん
Sami, are you OK?
サミ　大丈夫？
Shall I carry you on my back?
おぶってあげようか？
No, thanks!
いいもんっ！
Mom,
ママ
we're yet to see Mr. Grassho?
バッタさん　まだ？
Soon you will.
もうすぐよ
Only a few steps left, keep at it!
だからあとちょっと頑張ろう
Hey!
よ〜し！
Let's go for it!
こうすりゃ早いぞ
Masoo, thank you.
マソオさん　すみません
You're welcome.
いいんですよ
I have lost my child in an accident by the sea of sand.
俺も砂の海の事故でガキを亡くしてますんでね
Since then I love every small child.
小さい子供はほっとけないんですよ
Excuse me, Kuchiba.
あの…クチバさん
It's painful.
痛いです
What?
え？
You hold my hand too hard.
手　強く握り過ぎですよ
Ah! So..Sorry!
あっ！　す…すいません
Still yet?
まだかなあ
What's up?
どうしたの？
Have you seen?
…見えたの
Grassho? Where?
バッタ？　どこ？
I entered the military academy when I was 7.
私は七つのときに軍の養成学校へ上がることになった
I headed to the dormitory with my family.
私と家族は学校の寮へ向かったの
And that was the day I parted from my family.
その日で彼らとは別れることになっていたけど
But for us, whose emotions have been taken away, we didn't even have a feeling.
感情を取られた私たちは大した感慨を覚えることもなかった
The way to the dorm was long and steep, and my luggage was heavy.
寮へ行く道は長く険しく　荷物は重かった
Stand up!
立ちなさい
How can you be a good soldier with that!
そんなことでは立派な兵隊にはなれない
I saw it!
見た！
Yes, I saw it.
俺　見たよ
I saw your memory inside that creature.
あの生き物の中で…そのときの君を
I was not even troubling with it.
ずっと…　どうでもいいことだったのに…
Why it becomes so painful to me?
なぜ　こんなに苦しくなるの…
Lykos,
リコス
you do have your heart in you.
君　ちゃんと心があるんじゃないか
The same!
同じだよ
We are the same.
俺たちはおんなじだ
Hey, maybe the mud whale
ねえ　いつか泥クジラは
will get to where your family live some day.
君の家族の所へたどりつくかもしれない
Also you will never be a soldier here.
それに泥クジラでは
You will never die in a fight here in the mud whale.
兵士になって戦って死んじゃったりしない
Lykos, let's stay here.
リコス　ここで暮らそう？
Chakuro.
チャクロ
What?
何？
I have something important to say to you.
私…あなたたちに言わなければならないことがあるの
This ship...
この船は…
Hey!
おい！
φάλαινα
φάλαινα
Fallaina.
「ファレナ」は…
I wonder where are they going to.
あいつら…どこ行くんだろうな
We wanna go somewhere far away!
俺たちもどこか遠い世界へ行きたい！
July 8, 93 S.S.
砂刑暦93年7月8日
We recognized a locust phenomenon.
飛蝗現象を確認
The crowd was flying above the mud whale with lights emitted.
群れは発光しながら泥クジラの上空を舞い続け
And they leaved for somewhere far away in the sea of sand by the dawn.
明け方には砂の海の彼方へ旅立っていった
Chakuro!
チャクロー！
Get up now, take your breakfast!
さっさと起きろ　飯だ
Oh shit, you dumb-ass!
ああもう　てめえぇ！
I've had enough!
いいかげんにしろっ！
I can't stand teaming with you any longer!
お前なんかとおんなじ班はもう懲り懲りだっ
Troubling me all the time, you destroyer!
迷惑ばっかかけやがって　このデストロイヤーが
Tobi, listen.
トビ…言っとくけど…
Since our parents died,
俺や君たちの両親が亡くなって
we started to live together.
俺たちが共同生活をするようになってから
I have been looking after your younger brother and sister, haven't I?
俺は君の弟や妹の面倒を見てきたんだよ？
We are helping each other, right?
お互いさまってやつじゃないの？
Chakuro, you're sprinkling.
チャクロ　こぼちてる
You have been looked after, haven't you!
面倒見られてるじゃねーか…
How dare you call it helping each other!
何がお互いさまだー！
I'm heading the farm!
俺　畑の当番だ
It's my duty today!
いってきま〜す！
Suo.
スオウ
Bro~
お兄ちゃ〜ん
Wah, my bro's full of mud.
わっ　お兄ちゃん泥だらけ
I can't work as fast as you.
私は皆より作業が遅いから
So I started earlier.
先に来て進めてたんだよ
Where?
あれ？
My bro is good at everything except for physical fitness.
お兄ちゃんは運動神経が鈍いのが玉にキズなんだよね
Let's sow together.
俺たちは種まきしよう
The locust yesterday is really beautiful.
昨日の飛蝗　きれいだったね
Yeah.
うん
How about Lykos after that?
あのあと　リコスはどうしたの？
I sent her back to the central tower.
中央塔に送ってったよ
Since I brought her out secretly.
内緒で連れ出したからね
I see.
そっか
Sami, Chakuro,
サミ　チャクロ
do me a favor please.
あとはお願い
I have works to do at the presbytery.
私は長老会のお手伝いがあるから
OK!
は〜い
So.. sorry.
ご…ごめん
Fine.
ううん
Neli?
ネリ？
Suo.
スオウさん
What's wrong?
どうしたの？
That is...
それが…
Lykos said she has something to tell the presbyters.
リコスさんが長老様方にお話があるって
She seems very serious.
とても思い詰めた様子なんです
However, the presbytery refused to meet her.
それなのに　長老会は面会を拒否されておいでで…
And in fact...
実は…
The presbytery has sent the vigilante group out behind Taisha-sama.
長老会はタイシャ様には内緒で
It seems that they are alerting the surrounding sea areas.
自警団を海に出して周囲を警戒しているようなんです
Let me see her.
私が彼女に会いましょう
You can't.
ダメですよ
She is guarded and nobody is allowed to meet her.
誰にも会わせるなって見張りもついてるんですよ？
What do you want?
何か御用ですか？
You can't enter.
中へは入れませんよ
I have the permission.
私は許可を受けています
Er, I've never heard it...
そっ　そんな話は聞いてな…
You heard it just now.
今　聞いたことになさい
Right?
ね？
Excuse me, I...
失礼します　私は…
Please! Let me talk to the representative of this island!
お願い　この島の代表と話をさせて！
I have something important that I must tell you!
大事な…伝えなければならないことがあるの
Tell me please.
私が聞きましょう
Taisha-sama.
タイシャ様
I accidentally threw away Chakuro's records.
チャクロの記録が飛ばされてしまいました
I have to pick them up.
取りに行かないと
I will let others do it for you.
ほかの者を行かせますよ
That boy said he want to know the world,
あの子は世界を知りたいから
so he keeps the records.
記録を残すと言っていました
I have the same feeling now.
私も今は同じ気持ちです
However...
それなのに…
The presbytery is hiding the girl of the adrift island from us.
長老会は　流れ島の少女を私たちから隠そうとしています
We have no choice.
仕方ありません
The presbytery is conventionally controlling over the mud whale.
泥クジラの舵取りは　長老会がするしきたりです
Yeah, I do understand.
ええ　分かっています
Every "Muin" can become the presbyter when over 61 years old.
無印は61歳以上になると　全員長老会の構成員となる
Then they'll be informed with the history of mud whale
そして　泥クジラの歴史と世界の繋がりについて　知らされる
Chief doesn't have any political power.
首長には政治権力がなく
I'm only required to be a symbol being loved by the public.
ただ民たちに愛される象徴であることを求められる
There are 19 years before I can enter the presbytery.
私が長老会に入るまで　あと19年
Before that, I'm just a puppet.
それまで操り人形のように
I have to keep playing as a well-made idol.
よくできた偶像を演じ続けなければならない…
It... It isn't that bad!
よ…よいではないですか！
I don't care Taisha-sama is a puppet or not.
タイシャ様が人形だろうと何だろうと私は…
I always support you!
ずっとあなたをお支えします！
If it's for the sake of mud whale,
泥クジラのためならばこそ
I will try to be a good puppet.
いい人形になりましょう
What's that?
何だ？
σκύλος
スキロス　作戦行動に入ります
Escape from here, as soon as possible!
ここから逃げて！できるだけ早く！
This island...
この島は…
φάλαινα
φάλαινα
Fallaina...
「ファレナ」は…
Chakuro, is that a sand dolphin?
チャクロ　あれって砂イルカかな
You,
あなたたちは…
φάλαινα
ファレナ
The sinners of the whale, are targeted.
「鯨の罪人たち」は　狙われている…
Sinners?
罪人？
We are?
私たちが？
My records as the official record clerk
私の　記録係としての公式の記録は
ended this day.
この日が最後となった
The record about the mud whale, in the future,
この先の泥クジラにまつわる記録は
will be my personal
私の個人的な…
diary.
日記である
乾いた海の跡　望んで
乾いた海の跡　望んで
まだ見ぬ対岸を描く
まだ見ぬ対岸を描く
囚われの心のままなら
囚われの心のままなら
こんな傷みも知らずにいた
こんな傷みも知らずにいた
美しい詞を告げたひと
美しい詞を告げたひと
夜明けも待たずに
夜明けも待たずに
果てのその先を泳ぐ
果てのその先を泳ぐ
虫の唄
虫の唄
眠らず君と聞いた記憶
眠らず君と聞いた記憶
手を　ただ結んで
手を　ただ結んで
半色でも　遠い国でも
半色でも　遠い国でも
短い一章に生まれた夢を
短い一章に生まれた夢を
抱きしめに行こう
抱きしめに行こう